

Marco Virgolin

Spadinalaan 213, 1031 KB, Amsterdam 🏫

+31 628 735 831 📞

marco.virgolin@gmail.com

marco-virgolin-8815a667 in

@marcovirgolin 🛂

marcovirgolin (7)

https://marcovirgolin.github.io

I am a senior data scientist at Ingka, IKEA. I mainly focus on digital ethics and responsible AI, using and developing tools such as transformers, reinforcement learning, evolutionary computation. In the past, I have also worked on symbolic regression, neural architecture search, and human-machine interaction.

Core skills

- Strong analytical thinking & problem solving
- Conceptualization, execution, and supervision of machine learning research projects
- Develop. of libraries & pipelines, benchmarking
- Communication & presentation skills
- Pragmatic, flexible, result-oriented

Experience

MAR 2023 - ONGOING

Senior data scientist / Ingka – IKEA, Amsterdam, NL

I work in the digital ethics and responsible AI team. Our team's focus is on making data and AI processes trustworthy and accountable, as well as designing and training new valuable, explainable-by-design AI models.

SEP 2021 - MAR 2023

Researcher (tenure track) / CWI, Amsterdam, NL

I worked on the intersection between **evolutionary optimization** with machine learning, including **deep learning** (transformers, CNNs). I also studied methods to explain black-box ML models, such as **counterfactual explanations**. Besides this, I was involved in education and supervision (M.Sc. and Ph.D. students), as well as **international scientific collaborations**.

JUN 2020 - AUG 2021

Postdoc / TU Chalmers, Gothenburg, SE

I worked on making **natural language processing** more interpretable, and compared with **large language models**. I also worked on making interpretable ML more personalized with **active learning** and **human-machine interaction**.

NOV 2019 - MAR 2020

Project researcher / CWI, Amsterdam, NL

Project on emotion recognition from facial expression for children. Since pediatric data is scarce, I worked on data augmentation via contrastive learning for deep CNNs.

AUG 2012 - SEP 2013

Web developer / Promoscience, Padriciano, IT

Part-time job during my M.Sc. studies. Being a small company, I wore many hats: from **front-end** to **back-end web development**, incl. building **REST services** and interfacing with **relational data bases**.

Education

JUN 2020

Ph.D. in Evolutionary ML / TU Delft, Delft, NL + CWI, Amsterdam, NL

Design and application of **information theory-based evolutionary algorithms** for learning interpretable **symbolic regression** models. The project application concerned **pediatric radiotherapy**.

MAR 2015

M.Sc. in Computer Engineering / University of Trieste, Trieste, IT

Graduated **cum laude**. Courses ranging from theory of computability and complexity, to software engineering for web apps, IoT. Thesis on natural language processing via genetic programming, later published as a paper.

Honors

- Won SIGEVO Best Ph.D. Dissertation award in 2020, HUMIES Silver award in 2021, 2×Best paper awards
- Served in the program committee of several conferences and workshops: GECCO, ECML-PKDD, PPSN,
 Trustworthy and Socially Responsible Machine Learning Workshop @ NeurIPS, Workshop on eXplainable
 Knowledge Discovery in Data Mining @ ECML-PKDD, and more
- Served as a **reviewer** for several **international peer-reviewed journals**: Machine Learning, IEEE Transactions on Evolutionary Computation, Soft Computing, and more
- Invited in 2022 to be an evaluation committee member for the Dutch Research Council in the domain Science
- Recipient as co-applicant of a 300,000 SEK grant by Area of Advance Health Engineering, TU Chalmers 2021
- Recipient of 3 ACM Student travel grant during my Ph.D.
- Gave talks and invited lectures at multiple venues, incl. conferences, University of Amsterdam, TU Delft, MIT

Coding experience

Languages, from proficient to rusty: Python (incl. Pandas, Scikit-learn, PyTorch, NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Jupyter Notebooks), C++ (incl. Boost and SWIG to interface C++ with Python), C# (incl. ASP.NET), Java (incl. Android development), Matlab, PHP, SQL (MySQL and SQL Server), Javascript (incl. jQuery, AngularJS, NodeJS)

Examples of different open-source repos (see https://github.com/marcovirgolin):

- <u>GP-GOMEA</u> is a C++ based library which includes several symbolic regression algorithms with a Scikit-learn
 Python interface. These algorithms were found to be among the best performing in <u>SRBench</u> (NeurIPS 2021),
 a large benchmarking platform (which I co-authored and help maintaining).
- Robust-counterfactuals is a Python repository to simulate perturbations that may invalidate counterfactual
 explanations (a popular explainable AI method) and includes interfaces to experiment with different
 counterfactual search algorithms and machine learning models.
- **genepro** is a (documented) Python library that I prepared for TU Delft students for the course *Evolutionary Algorithms* of 2021-2022. It contains examples for **classification**, **regression**, and **reinforcement learning**.

Other info

- I was a **co-organizer** of the <u>Joint Lectures on Evolutionary Algorithms</u> (JoLEA), in particular I prepared and maintain the website, and I set up a MailChimp account for mailing lists and tweets.
- I served in ASTRO (2014-2015), a **volunteering** association for helping with care for hospitalized children.
- An academic version of my CV is available on my website.
- In my free time I enjoy bouldering.